<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The funerall-sermon of Mr. Miles Pinckeney alias Thomas Carre confessour to the English canonesses regulars of the holly Order of S. Augustin established in Paris. / Preached to the sayd religious at his solemn funeralls by his successour E.L.</title>
            <author>Lutton, Edward, 1637 or 8-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B26345</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">48173050</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207674</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240873271</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3519A</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">48173050</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B26345)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1928:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The funerall-sermon of Mr. Miles Pinckeney alias Thomas Carre confessour to the English canonesses regulars of the holly Order of S. Augustin established in Paris. / Preached to the sayd religious at his solemn funeralls by his successour E.L.</title>
                  <author>Lutton, Edward, 1637 or 8-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Vincent Du Moutier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Paris, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LXXV. [1675]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Head and tail pieces.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Carre, Thomas, 1599-1674.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207674:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207674:2"/>
            <p>THE FUNERALL-SERMON OF M<seg rend="sup">R</seg> MILES PINCKENEY <hi>ALIAS</hi> THOMAS CARRE Confessour to the English Canonesses Regulars of the holly Order of <hi>S.</hi> Augustin established in Paris.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preached to the sayd Religious at his solemn Funeralls by his Successour E. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT PARIS, BY VINCENT DU MOUTIER, M. DC. LXXV. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>PERMISSION</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:207674:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207674:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:207674:4"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:207674:4"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVLY VENERABLE LADY ABBESSE <hi>MARIE TREDWAY:</hi> TO THE VERY REVERENDE MOTHER <hi>DOROTHEE MOLINS;</hi> And all the Religious daughters of Sion, the English Cannonesses Regulars of the holly Order of S. Augustin established in Paris.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MOST H<seg rend="sup">d</seg> LADY, VERY R<seg rend="sup">de</seg> MOTHER, &amp; RELIGIOVS SISTERS.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AD I bin as ready to give the Publicke a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of my folly, as I was always willing the World might know how much I esteeme &amp; respect you, I would long since have found some meanes to have gott into Print; but, I thanke God, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found my self transported with that imagination; contrary waise, I am perswaded that had I experienced any kind of tickling cawsed by the conceipt of getting into the Presse, I should have chosen rather to have spett upon the thought, and so have kill'd that itch, then expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed my self to have bin scratcht in publicke. 'Tis upon this account, that as I most willingly Preface this sheet of paper to give a publicke testimony of the most cordiall esteeme and respect I have for you, so am I not unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to lett the Reader know, 'tis you will needs trouble him with it. I must confesse I can not well imagin and frame to my self an occasion w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> could more powerfully force me to what I doe not much relish, I mean appearing in Print, then this which hath now putt me upon it, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:207674:5"/>making this little Memoriall of worthy Mr Carre's deserts become the subject of a dutifull testimony of your Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. To me (and I thinke other men are much of that humour) there is nothing so acceptable and pleasing as a Gratefull minde. 'Tis true that the rendring any services, or doing any favours out of a craving hope of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded or even thanked for them, is indeed Trafike ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Freindship, neverthelesse there are few men who take satisfaction to see their kindenesse and freind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship wholly lost,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tium post <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ficium est <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ficii sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> which yet are never more truly cast away, then when thrown upon an Vngratefull hart. This consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration easily excuseth to me your eagernesse for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing this paper; and I beleive will justify the same in the thoughts of others, who certainly, whatever they shall thinke of my Composition, will allow of your Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>As for this little discourse its being address'd to you, I thinke no body will much finde fault therewith, because it seemes very justly due to you, both upon the account of its Subject, and its Authour. Me thinkes it is a very equitable congruity to Dedicate to you an half-hower's discourse of that life, fourty years whereof had bin dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to your assistance and advantage. And for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, there is much the same reason, because, though he pretends not to his Predecessour's excellent qualities and endowments for your help and service, yet doth he (and hopes without offence) to an equality of good will and and best wishes, or, which is the same, to be, as that worthy person was, most entierly Yours in JESVS-CHRIST.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:207674:5"/>
            <head>THE FVNERALL-SERMON OF M<seg rend="sup">R</seg> MILES PINCKENEY <hi>ALIAS</hi> THOMAS CARRE &amp;c. <hi>Viae Sion lugent.</hi> Thren. 1.4. <hi>Syon in mourning.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ERE Love and Gratitude to be regulated by Ceremony, the solemnity of this day would putt an end-to your just mourning, Religious Sisters. In the written law 30 days was the usuall time for bewayling the deaths of great men, and freinds, as appears by the last chapter of Deuteronomie, and other passages of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Testament. And in our dayes, alas! how many, after the last solemn ringing of the bells, ly as still in the memory of their freinds, as they doe in the cold beds of their silent Graues!<note place="margin">Ps. 9.</note>
               <hi>periit memoria eorum cum sonitu:</hi> sometimes their being thus suddainly forgotten is occasioned by their own mean deserts, but many times 'tis their misfortune to have so ungratefull fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inds as to bury them in their Harts almost as soone as in the Earth, to whom we may with some kind of compassion appropriate the Epithet of the Royall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and call them <hi>mortuos à corde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ps. 30.</note> But our worthy Deceased, whose solemn funeralls this Noble and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>indly company is pleased this day to celebrate and honour; the worthy Deceased, I say, the world knows
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:207674:6"/>was not so little deserving in himself as to be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly forgotten; and I dare assure the world not so unhappy in his freinds as to be buryed in oblivion as soone as layd in his Grave. I dare say the days of Mourning which you designe him will have no other measure then those of your life, and the gratefull me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of Him will never dy in you, but with you: so that I thinke its needlesse for me to use any other meanes to gaine your favorable attention, then to tell you that the subject of this little discourse is some of the many of deceased M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's excellent qualities in himself, and goodnesses to you, which as you now love to remember, so you will allwayes remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to love. I shall speake but of some of his many excellent endowments, and that with all the breifty that is possible, both that the present Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may not proue too tedious to those his freinds who understand me,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>This was sayd in order to the French who were present.</hi> 1. Cor. 14. Ovid.</note> and that I may not prove intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably importune to those, to whom, because they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand me not, I am, according to S. Paul's expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion a barbarian, <hi>ero ei cui loquor barbarus;</hi> and the Poet <hi>barbarus his ego sum quia non intelligor ulli;</hi> and who, for want of understanding me, can not, as otherwaise they would, say <hi>Amen</hi> to the known truths I intend to insist upon.</p>
            <p>It hath bin a frequent conduct of allmighty God to foretell the eminent greatnesse of some of his servants by very particular effects of his Providence and Grace, either at their birth, their calling, or their conversion. Thus Abraham being designed for the first father of the faithfull was miraculously call'd out of the land of Vr; was treated by allmighty God with a particular fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity, blest with a miraculous issue, &amp; the rest. Moyses was miraculously preserved from perishing in the Nile; was miraculously brought up in Pharao's own Court, whilst that proud and hard-harted King was contriving the totall extirpation of the innocent Israelites; and when call'd to his strange Mission for conducting the children of Israel into the desert▪ it was by the mira<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207674:6"/>burning of a bush without consuming. S. John-Baptist being designed for the Precursour of CHRIST was sanctifyed in his Mother's womb, and his dumb father restored to his speech at his birth. And S. Paul being to be the great Apostle of Christianity was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculously struck off his Persecutour's horse, and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by Christ himself in his devine Apostleship. And to come to my present subject, I thinke I may say so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mething of this nature of our worthy Deceased. But mistake me not, Noble and Courteous Auditours, I doe not pretend to make exorbitant paralells between great Saints and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre; I can not forbear to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse my self too great an enimy to sordid flattery, and must owne M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre too great a freind to a certain plain truth, and an honest uprightnesse, to use such hyperbolicall extravagancies upon his account. I must confesse my very worthy and much obliging freind was very unhappy to fall into such poor hands as mine to have his deserverd prayses sett forth; but yet it shall not be so very ill neither, and which I am confident he would have esteemed the basest of all pretended good-offices, I meane he shall not be flattered: and yet some thing of this nature may stand with truth, and I without any flattery may say, his Conversion had some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of extraordinary, and thence inferre that God had intended him an Instrument of very much good. It was his misfortune to have spent his childhood and some part of his youth in a Church which hath unhappily divided herself from that Church which God had most graciously designed him to be a considerable member of, which he effected by bringing him to see a possest person exercised by a Roman-Catholike Priest: the poor possest gave such testimonies of his misfortune, that the sad truth was altogether unquestionable: and the wicked spirit's strange subjection to the Priest's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands was a great conviction that the sacred spirit of God must needs be in that Church, whose Pastours and Ministers could so command the wicked spirits of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:207674:7"/>Devills. You know that, according to our Saviour's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, dispossessing of Devills is done by the fingar of God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uc. 11.</note>
               <hi>si in digito Dei ejicio Daemonia,</hi> now this fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar of God could not but point out to our deceased his true Church: and 'twas very easy for him to know which was the true company of the faithfull by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring what he had seen,<note place="margin">Mar. 16.</note> with what Christ had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, <hi>signa autem eos qui crediderint haec sequentur, in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine meo Daemonia eijcient.</hi> Nor can it be reasonably objected that his youth made him foolishly Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; those who were acquainted with his temper knew him to be farre from so weake an humour as to be easily imposed upon; and his remembring that passage with much admiration even in his old age, is a strong confirmation of the reasonable proceeding of his youth. But this was only a signe and foretelling that God had designed him for some very particular Good, and that was to be yours, Religious sisters, whose Beginning, Proceeding, and Present condition owes very much to Mr Carre's Wisdome and Labour, his Learning and Piety.</p>
            <p>And to begin with his Wisdome: As the Art of Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is the greatest of all Arts, so the greatest of all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vertues is necessary for its happy performance, I meane that great and universall vertue, call'd Prudence, or a practicall Wisdome; 'Twas this vertue which still lookes round about her, and is so necessary for Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours that the spirit of God (which alone knowes what we ought to pray for) made the great King Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon petition for,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 9.</note>
               <hi>Da mihi sedium tuarum assistricem sapientiam ut mecum sit, &amp; mecum laboret.</hi> Graunt me ô Lord! that the heavenly wisdome which always waites at thy devine Throne, may never desert me, but may always stand by me, inspire and assist me in all my difficulties, and all my labours: a petition extreame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gratefull to the devine Majesty, who therefor most copiously replenished his Royall Hart therewith, whom he had designed for a great and glorious King: and I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:207674:7"/>thinke we may with much truth say that the same God bestowed some measure of the same spirit upon M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre whom he had designed for an undertaking which stood in much need of that assistance. I say nothing of his sharpe and peircing iudgment, his excellent good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and admirable discernment. I passe over the great and constant assistance you always had of his wise advice and counseils in troublesome and pinching circumstances, which, I thinke, still proued so happy, as you hardly ever had reason to repent your having harkened thereunto. These and the like effects of his singular Wisdome I passe over, and will content my self to insist only on one. 'Twas a hard taske! for a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man, a stranger, one that neither had riches to purchase, nor yet such great alliance as might procure the credit which seemed necessary for the undertaking which M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre had so couragiously ventured upon: so that if we reflect on the great and considerable Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit he had gained himself, I thinke it must needs be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to a singular Wisdome and discretion, which is a participation of that holly Spirit the wise Salomon so earnestly pray'd for, that he might be enabled for a worthy governing the people of God.<note place="margin">My Lord Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot Montagu.</note> Who knows not M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's particular credit with that Pious, Excellent Noble-man, whose Modesty will not allow me to name him, who may be known by that of the Joseph of our Nation, the common Father of the distressed poor En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish. 'Tis true, and I can not but acknowledg it, his Goodnesse is easily gain'd, he is of very facile accesse, and a man needs nothing to gaine his favour, but only to want his Protection: but yet the Credit our worthy Deceased had with him was very particular, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he pretended nothing but the honour of being esteemed his faithfull poor servant, and look'd upon as one that might deserve his Protection both for his pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and his person, yet was he honoured by him with a most particular esteeme, nay I dare add a Freindship, which he was pleased to give a signall testimony of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207674:8"/>when he thought fitt to trust him with what is most sacred and most dear to us, the performance and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of our last wills and Testaments. It is also very well known how considerable his Credit was with that great and famous man the late deceased Chancellour of France. It must needs be a very particular effect of God's Goodnesse, and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's wise Conduct that a good honest Priest, a private English-man, a poor Stranger should so ingratiate himself with that eminent person as to be treated by him with a most particular familiarity, when so many great and considerable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of the Kingdome esteemed themselves extreame happy in being only taken notice of by him. Our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased could upon occasions haue speedy Audience, and be treated with a most freindly kindnesse, whilst persons of great note were forced to come frequently, waite long, and in the end hardly have one word ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their wish and desire. This certainly was very much, but not all: our late Queen-Mother of pious and sacred memory voutsafed not only most graciously to take notice of him, but further made appear that her Majesty thought his concerns not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of her appearing in them, and his person not unworthy of her Royall Protection. Thus we often read in holly Scripture that those, whom Allmighty God intended for the assistance and releif of his afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted people were by him ingratiated with the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Princes of the places where they were, as Joseph with Putiphar, and Pharao himself in Egypt for the releif of his old father Jacob with his Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren the Patriarchs; and the good Tobie, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Israelites in the Assyrian captivity, with the tryumphant Prince King Salmanasar. What I haue now sayd of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre, are truths which many know although with a kind of an unconcerned speculation, but you, Religious Sisters, by a happy gainefull experience of the many favours, bounties, liberalities, and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the mentioned great persons, which was M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:207674:8"/>Carre's maine endeavour, whose principall end was only to become instrumentall to your happinesse, and as it were, the channell by which all the freinds he could make should discharge their bounties and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours upon you. I passe over the great Credit he had with many others of lesser note, which yet proued very necessary for your establishment and subsistance: the dreadfull civill warres both in England and this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which caused a kind of an universall desolation, were sad circumstances for the beginning of your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastery: your freinds in England in an impossibility of succouring you, and times in France so deplorable, that had not M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's Credit supplyed your necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, you must have broke up almost as soone as you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to keepe house, and your Monastery must have sunke in its very foundations.</p>
            <p>But M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's Credit, which his wise Conduct had procured, was not beneficiall to you only; his industry, his paines, his labours for your advantage were so great and so many, that I dare not enter into all the particulars, they alone would take up much more time, then I dare allott my self for the whole discourse; I may tell you in short that all M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's life was a continuall series of paines and labours for your good and advantage, and although it pleased God, for your good also, to bring him to a faire age, yet certainly the labours of his young days shortned his old ones, and the continuall tourmoiles of his life putt him into a fitt of a languishing sicknesse, which lasted above twelue years, and at length brought him to his Graue. Moyses crossed the red sea but once, to lead the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Israel into the Desert, but M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre crossed our English seas 56 times, and that principally to bring you into this happy Solitude, this spiritual Desert, where he conducted you for the space of 40 years, &amp; fed you with the heavenly Manna of the holly Sacraments, and pious Instructions in Solid Christianity: but, to be as good as what I professed of not extravagantly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207674:9"/>him to great Saints, I am farre from pretending the stupendious and miraculous proceedings in the one which we read of the other. As our Deceased was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any pretender to Miracles, so neither doe I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any upon his account, unlesse we may, in some measure, say of this poor house what S. Augustin hath sayd of Christianity it self, that the greatest miracle which God wrought in order to the establishing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was its establishment. Once again, I say, I doe not pretend to any miracles, but yet I thinke this Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery's establishment had something of particular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. What? for 4 or 5 persons to come into a strange Country to make a perpetuall settlement with ten pistolls? The effect shew what the undertaking was in M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre, but in an ordinary person, I know what it must needs have bin thought, especially if there be any establishing of Monasteries, as well as building of Castles, in the Air. But 'twas M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's laborious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry and industrious labours which made that a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible and glorious undertaking in him, which would have bin an absurd and egregious folly in an other. God allmighty had not only enriched M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre with many great Talents, he further bestowed on him se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Mnas, many lesser sort of endowments, which all contributed to the compassing his great underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: we read in Exodus that the same God particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inspired Beseleel and Ooliab with a knowledg and insight into all sorts of workes and contrivances which were necessary for the making and compleating of the Arke, which knowledges and Arts allmighty God calls his own devine spirit,<note place="margin">r. 31.</note>
               <hi>implevi eum spiritu Dei, sapientiâ, &amp; intelligentiâ, &amp; scientiâ in omni opere:</hi> and I hope it will be no extravagancy in me to say something of this nature of our Deceased: his perfect knowledg, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable insight, and excellent skill in bookes, painting, sculpture, cutts in brasse, and the like, were as well known, as they were very necessary, and seemed ins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired by God for compleating the great worke he had
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207674:9"/>ventured upon, the setting up this little spirituall Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of Alliance, especially considering the lamentable circumstances of its beginning which I have hinted at.<note place="margin">Serm. 26. in Cant.</note> We may with much truth say of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre what S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard sayd in his admirable Funerall-Sermon upon the excellent and vertuous Monke Gerard, his Brother both in blood and Religion, <hi>Nec in maximis tantùm, sed &amp; in minimis maximus erat,</hi> he was not only excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent at great things,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caementariis, fabris, agricolis hortulanis, su toribus atque textoribus faci le Magister erat.</hi> id. ibid.</note> he was also admirable at little ones: and seeing S. Bernard tooke the paines to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his Brother extreamely for his skill in Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecture, Husbandry, Gardens, Waters, nay even some of the meanest Mechanikes, I thinke we may with great reason give M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre his due commendations for the liberall knowledges and ingenuous skills, which I have spoken of, particularly since employed for so commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable an end. 'Twas M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's particular insight, knowledg, and skill in the things I have mentioned, joyned with his unspeakable toyles, and indefatigable industry which strangely concurr'd to the setling and carying on of this Monastery, so that I thinke we may very justly apply to him that of the Royall Prophet <hi>in intellectibus manuum suarum deduxit eas.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ps. 77.</note> His daily run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning about, his constant care and contrivances, his continuall labours, which very frequently tooke up the time even of rest, and other necessary refreshments, principally contribured to getting these stones toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the raysing up of these walls, so that, in the well known impossible supposition that he could be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by those he hath so much deserved of, and that these his gratefull children (I still speake in a wild and impossible supposition) could refuse his memory their just acknowledgments, the stones would speake,<note place="margin">Lucae 19.</note>
               <hi>si hae tacuerint, lapides clamabunt:</hi> so that in my opinion, Religious Sisters, we needed not to have bin so very sollicitous what piththy Remembrance should have bin written ouer his Grave: every stone will proue a stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding monument, and gratefull memory will read in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207674:10"/>every part of this building a glorious Epitaphe of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's constant paines and continuall labours.</p>
            <p>But yet the excellent qualities which I have heither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lightly touched upon, were not the principall. We must looke upon his undertaking as twofold; he had two buildings to raise up, two howses to establih, a materiall, and a spirituall one: His endowments which I have mentioned, were very necessary for the one, but, in my opinion, not so very considerable but in as much as they related to the other: the first was but, as it were, the body of his design, which only ought to be esteemed in order to the soule, which was the spirituall edifice he had to raise up,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Haebr. 3.</note>
               <hi>Domum non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactam..... quae Domus estis vos,</hi> to speake in S. Paul's language, a house not raised up with hands, a spirituall house made up of your selves, Religious Sisters. This was M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's principall worke, this was his great Master-peice: for the effecting whereof Learning and Vertue were absolutely and equally necessary, and were so conspicuous in M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre, that it will be a very easy taske for me to make good things so evident and so publick.</p>
            <p>For his Learning you can produce convicting proofs, I meane your little Libraries, a great part whereof consists in the products of his pious learning: The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations which he hath compiled for your dayly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall-prayer, and spirituall employment, for your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats, Cloathings, Professions, and what not? The many Miscelaneous treatises, disputations, explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and instructions: the severall workes of the Devout and truly Religious Thomas of Kempis which he hath made yours, by making them intelligible to you. Nay he was not content to employ his Learning for the spirituall good of your House only, he farther engaged his pen for the honour and concerne of your whole Order, joyned with the learned P. Fronteau and writt a booke to maintain that admirable worke which relisheth so devoutly to every ones gust, the Imitation
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:207674:10"/>of Christ,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iugement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictoire de Messicurs des Requestes du Palais au Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement de Paris apres six Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences le</hi> 12. <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vrier</hi> 1652.</note> to have bin writt by Thomas of Kempis a Canon-Regular of the Order of S. Augustin: which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking prou'd so succesfull that a favorable sentence was given for our Deceased his pretentions, and a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory prohibition for the printing of the sayd worke under his name, whom our adverse partie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, but in vaine. Besides your House and your Order, our whole Nation is beholding to him for the <hi>Piety of Paris</hi> composed by him: the devine booke of the <hi>Love of God</hi> severall of Cardinall de Richelieu's workes, the <hi>Draught of Eternity,</hi> and many others were by him taught to speake english for English-mens sakes. Not only your particular House, not only your whole Order, not only our whole Nation is beholding to him, he hath further well deserved of the whole Church of God by the severall workes he hath composed for the vindication of its sacred Faith against the mistaken zeale and false conceipts of some of her enimies.</p>
            <p>His Vertue was nothing inferiour to his Learning: he most eminently deserved the title which we usually bestow upon a man we thinke deserves a syncere and cordiall commendation, and whom we call an Honest man: An encomium that sounds but little, yet says very much: it meanes one that goes streight before him, a Candid, Syncere, Vpright man: a worthy mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of human society, one that deserves to be trusted and confided in. A precious thing in this our Age, where there is so much cunning, intriguing, dissembling, double-dealing, and covert driuing on of private desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes and interests, that 'tis almost as hard for an honest plainly-meaning man to finde an other to fix and rely upon, as it was for Archimedes to finde a place out of the world to sett his Engine upon, with which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have moved the Machine of the whole Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse: and yet the God of goodnesse and charity, for the entertaining thereof between man and man, would have them stand in need of their mutuall help and the assistance of each other, and there is hardly that man
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:207674:11"/>so stored with temporall blessings as never stands in need of an others freindship, counseil, or the like assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance. 'Tis upon this account that I dare say the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish world had a considerable losse in M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre, whose just proceedings, upright and honest behaviour were as well known as his name, men usually putt them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and the word was, HONEST M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> CARRE. The great dealings, the many emploiments, which the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances he was in unavoydably putt him upon; the vast trusts and confidences our miserable times occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned him to be tryed with, were excellent tests of the Honest man I have spoken of, and who gave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable testimonies of his being such, since in all these great and many occasions no man was ever a loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser, except himself, who still preferr'd to suffer, rather then an other should who had thought him fitt to be trusted and confided in. His advice and counseils were of the same straine with his Trust, honest and upright: Worth, Truth, and Vertue were still the measures of his proceedings, so that none came more dissatisfied with him, then those who desired to be flattered by him. 'Twas the great maxime of his proceedings that Truth and honesty would still be justified, and beare up at last, however for a while trampled upon, so that his motto should have bin <hi>Magna est Veritas &amp; praeva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> Great is Truth and alwayes prevalent. This was his proceeding in order to those who thought fitt to confide either their affaires to his conduct and trust, or themselves to his aduice and counseils. Those who stood in need of the assistance of his purse were not more unhappy, and 'tis hard to say whether were grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his uprightnesse and honesty, or his compassion and charity: hardly ever any one craved it that was refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it, but many had the comfort of enjoying it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the confusion of begging it. When he had it not in money; his bookes, pictures, cloaths were sold, any thing so the Poor were releived; and because the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of Christ of still having Poor amongst us hath of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:207674:11"/>late years bin so plentifully fulfill'd, when his goods could not reach to help the needy, his Credit was to be employed for them, and principally with that Vertuous Noble-man I haue hinted at: he knows ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well that although our Deceased had many occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions to trouble him for his Credit and Assistance, yet did he never more frequently importune him upon any account, then the releiving the Poor. Great comfort in order to our Deceased! especially if we may in any sort rely upon that passage of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of that worke putt amongst those of S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin, and intituled <hi>sermones ad fratres in Eremo;</hi> the sayd passage is the beginning of the 44. chapter, and runs in these termes; <hi>numquam recordor me legisse ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lâ morte periisse illum qui libenter opera Charitatis vel pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis exerceret.</hi> I doe not remember ever to have read that a harty charitable man ever dyed a bad death and perished: and the reason he adds is, <hi>multos habet intercessores,</hi> he hath many to plead and intercede for him. 'Tis upon this account that I can not forbeare to professe what I was most pleased and satisfyed with at his Buriall. He had indeed the honour to be accompanied to his Graue by many persons of note, and severall of eminent quality. 'Twas a Civility equall to their Quality, very Great, and which chalengeth his freinds particular gratitude to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest in their due thankes and acknowledgments, but still the Goodnesse was theirs, <hi>honor est in honorante.</hi> 'Twas something to see the Corpse accompanied with great multitudes, and the Streets crowded with throughs of spectatours: but alas! some of these might be there out of mere Idlenesse, others by Chaunce, and some again out of Curiosity: but to heare severall of the Poor say; oh! he was a good man, he often releived me: he was truly charitable; we all loose a great freind, a common father: God reward him, God graunt him everlasting rest and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:207674:12"/>peace: that he may meet his Almes in heaven: that he may never want any thing in the next world, who so charitably releived ours in this. Oh! this a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table hearing; these are efficacious prayers for the Dead; these are powerfull Intercessours with the Devine Justice for a poor sinner,<note place="margin">Ps. 40.</note>
               <hi>habet multos Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessores. In die mala liberabit eum Dominus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be, after you have seen so much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion and tendernesse in his hart, you hardly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to finde much fortitude and magnanimity in his soule; and so you might indeed, had he bin molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Nature, more then by Charity; but such is the excellence of that vertue that she tempers our harts with so admirable a Meane, that we are at once hott and cold, soft and hard, sweet and sower, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and stiff, complying and inexorable. 'Twas thus that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre was soft and compassionate for the necessities of the poor, whilst he was resolute and unshakable for uprightnesse, justice, and truth: a great vertue in a person of his calling! Christian for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and Priestly magnanimity certainly is one of the most necessary vertues for persons of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, because there is nothing more ruinous to Christian Piety then the base Compliance of Priests. Their Vnchristian Cowardlinesse, their Vnpriestly Lasheté not only occasions, it incourages and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizeth Vice. 'Twas the want of this Priestly vertue of couragiously standing up for God's cause, when occasion should requier, that made great Prophets apprehend their Missions,<note place="margin">Exod. 3.</note> although immediatly sent from God himself: hence that of Moyses <hi>quis sum ego ut vadam ad Pharaonem, &amp; educam filios Israel?</hi> Who am I that shall dare speake to Pharao to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse the children of Israel?<note place="margin">Jer. 1.</note> that of the Prophet Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy <hi>A, a, a, Domine Deus, ecce, nescio loqui, quia puer ego sum.</hi> A, a, a, my Lord and God! A fine Missionair to be sent to thy people, poor child that I am who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:207674:12"/>can not speake. But those whom allmighty God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed for his servants, he still strengthned them with his devine assistance, and enabled them to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the frownes and fiercest lookes of their proud enimies.<note place="margin">Exod. 9.</note>
               <hi>Dixit Dominus ad Moysen ecce constitui te Deum Pharaonis.</hi> Moyses, saith our Lord, be of good courage, I have made thee proud Pharao's God: and to the Prophet Jeremie <hi>Ne timeas à facie eorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 1.</note>
               <hi>quia ego tecum sum ut eruam te dicit Dominus.</hi> Fear them not, I'l ever stand hy thee, and protect thee, sayth our Lord: or, as the Prophet Ezechiel expresseth it, <hi>ecce dedi faciem tuam valentiorem faciebus eorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 3.</note>
               <hi>&amp; frontem tuam duriorem frontibus eorum.</hi> I have given thee a face to outface their faces, which Tertullian calls a modest impudence, <hi>honestâ impudentiâ verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem annunciet nullius faciem reveritus.</hi> The exact pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of our Deceased: when Truth, Justice, and Vprightnesse were concerned, he fear'd no body; he never spared any, when there was a just occasion of telling them <hi>non licet tibi;</hi> 'tis not lawfull for you,<note place="margin">Marc, 6.</note> you must not. He hath upon occasions spoken with so much Christian libertie to persons of very great quality, whose freindship he valued infinitely, and no lesse stood in need of their favour and Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that had they not bin as considerable for their Vertue and Goodnesse, as they were for their Power and Greatnesse, he might have lost his Freinds and Patrons, and sacrificed his Satisfaction and Interest to Truth and Justice.</p>
            <p>But time calls upon me to make an end, and so I will, having first sayd one word concerning his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in order to the directing of you, Religious Sisters; and that was like the rest of his proceedings, upright, syncere, solid, and Christian: I thinke I may without any scandall or offence say, that he endeavoured to conduct you, as God doth the just man, <hi>per vias rectas</hi> by streight ways,<note place="margin">Sap. 10.</note> in the high
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:207674:13"/>rode, and beaten path of Christianity. His great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour was, that Tertullian's excellent expression should be verified in you, <hi>non magna loquimur, sed vivimus:</hi> he much rather wisht that men should read great things in your actions, then heare them in your discourses: nay you know his constant labour was that you should rather doe little things without pretending to great ones, then pretend to great matters, and not practise smale things. Enfine his great principle was, that your Religious Perfection was to consist in a Christian vanquishing your pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, and overcomming your imperfections; in an assiduous and constant performance of your Religious duties; in a worthy, respectfull approaching to the holly sacraments: in a modelling your selves in some measure after the great Originall of all Saints and Predestinate CHRIST-JESUS, and that, by copying out, by your practise, some of the Christian vertues, which alone can make us like Christ, Patience, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Meekenesse, Sweetnesse, Charity towards our Neighbour, together with a profound Esteeme, Respect, and Reverentiall Love of Allmighty God. These were the lessons and documents which he never ceased to inculcate to you, to settle and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print in your mindes, at all seasons, all times, all occasions,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.</note>
               <hi>opportunè importunè.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I must conclude, and I thinke I may with S. Bernard's words in his funerall sermon which I have already spoken of: <hi>Plango, primùm super mea ipsius plaga, atque hujus jactura Domus. Plango deinde super Pauperum necessitatibus, quorum...... pater erat. Plango certè &amp; super universo statu nostri ordinis, nostrae Professionis, qui de tuo..... zelo, consilio, &amp; exemplo ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bur non mediocre capiebat.</hi> I lament, first for my own and this poor house's losse; next for that of the Poor who had a father in him; and lastly for our whole body which received no smale advantage from his harty
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207674:13"/>zeale, his solid advice, and his Preistly example. For my part I have reason to bewaile M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's death for my own sake, because his Kindenesse to me hath bin almost of the same durance with my self. In my childehood he was pleased to charge himself with a care of me, and had an ey over me at my being but 8 years of age: he continued his Freindship towards me during the rest of his life, and gave me most signall tokens therof by the trust and confiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce he putt in me in his declining years, and at his Death. For you, Religious Sisters, what a losse you have had in him, the world knows very well, but you your selves yet better. All the endeavours of his body and minde seemed to be only for your advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: he seemed to live only for your good and assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, and having most earnestly recommended it to your and his noble Patron, as if then all had bin done, soon after he Dyed. He not only most hartily employed all he had, he employed himself also to the utmost of his power for your good and advantage.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Libentissimè im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendam, &amp; su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimpendar ipse.</hi> 2. Cor. 12.</note> But not to run a new into a subject which I have by meer force broke out of, I will content my self to tell you in short, that you have lost in M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre, a Freind, a Founder, a Father. For the Poor, they have lost a zealous Advocat, and a Cordiall Patron. And for our Body, I mean the Pastorall Hierarchicall Clergy of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> English Roman-Catholike Church it hath lost a very worthy and excellent member, and such as they have testified they would not have bin ashamed it should have bin their Head.</p>
            <p>But we are not come heither meerly to bewaile our losses in him, we are rather mett, some to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise their Religious charity; others to make their Christian returns for whatsoeuer he may have obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them in; wherfor lett us all joyne our harts and vows with the Priest; lett us all meet in spirit at the foot of the Altar to make the dread Sacrifice truly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207674:14"/>Propitiatory for all our Deceased's oversights, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and faylings; (for, alas! who hath not some? or rather who hath not many?) Lett us all joyne to beseech, and obtain of the Devine Majesty that all worthy M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Carre's charities, pieties, and goodnesses may now be gently showred down upon his own head in Eternall Glory: that all his Paines, Labours, and Toyles may be rewarded with everlasting Rest and Peace. Lett us all pray with holly Church <hi>sit in pace locus eius:</hi> that all his paines and labours in this world for you, Religious Sisters, may finde rest and peace in the next, <hi>sit in pace locus ejus:</hi> that all his labours and paines for rich and poor, gentle and sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, freinds and foes, for all, that all may be crown'd with Rest and Peace, <hi>sit in pace locus ejus. AMEN, AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:207674:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>